<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Forecast Analyst&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://owang-bio.github.io/ouwang.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Forecast Analyst&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 01:16:38 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://owang-bio.github.io/ouwang.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://owang-bio.github.io/ouwang.io/posts/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 01:16:38 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owang-bio.github.io/ouwang.io/posts/introduction/</guid>
      <description>This is my GitHub page where I post things that might be helpful for data analysts who regularly use Python and Excel.
The content will focus on specific functions, or libraries that are commonly used among data analysts, especially for those who deal with time series data. I may not include too much about the basics of programming and Python.
I will keep each blog as short as 3 to 5 minutes reading so if anyone would read it, they don&amp;rsquo;t get bored before finishing reading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python datetime module</title>
      <link>https://owang-bio.github.io/ouwang.io/python-for-forecast-analyst/date_functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 23:58:51 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owang-bio.github.io/ouwang.io/python-for-forecast-analyst/date_functions/</guid>
      <description>As a forecast analyst, I am dealing with time series data every day. So, the first Python module I want to mention is datetime which provides basic classes for dates and time manipulation.
For my current job, although I am helping several international markets, most of the time I don&amp;rsquo;t need to worry about time zone or daylight saving time, etc. If you are interested in the datetime type that include such information, you can learn more about it from the documentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Author</title>
      <link>https://owang-bio.github.io/ouwang.io/author/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 02:07:31 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owang-bio.github.io/ouwang.io/author/</guid>
      <description>I am John Doe and currently working as a forecast analyst. I have been learning data analytics every day and taking notes using Microsoft OneNote. I think it would be interesting if I make my notes public, which is why I am creating this blog. I will spend a couple of minutes everyday and write about something I have learned every day. Hope some of my blogs can be helpful to some of the people.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Admin Panel</title>
      <link>https://owang-bio.github.io/ouwang.io/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 02:07:30 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owang-bio.github.io/ouwang.io/admin/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>All Sections</title>
      <link>https://owang-bio.github.io/ouwang.io/sections/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 02:07:30 +0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owang-bio.github.io/ouwang.io/sections/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
